Guide to the Northern Virginia Music Center at Reston collection, 1967-1979
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Northern Virginia Music Center at Reston collection
1967-1979
C0191
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
3.5 linear feet (9 boxes)
The Northern Virginia Music Center at Reston collection contains correspondence, articles, photographs, and 56 audiotape reels related to music center. Photographs include both images of performances as well as publicity shots of the musicians.
Meir, Robert C.
Related Materials
Special Collections and Archives also holds many other collections on Reston, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The Northern Virginia Music Center at Reston, established in 1967, saw its faculty and students conduct and participate in yearly summer camps and concert series until 1973, when the Center dissolved. This collection documents the Center, and is divided into two series.
Series 1, Music Center Papers, 1967-1979, consists of correspondence, programs, articles, and photographs documenting the Center and its performances. Funding, budget, board minutes, member mailings, photographs, and resumes of musicians visiting the Center constitute the bulk of the materials in series 1. The photographs include both images of performances as well as publicity shots of musicians. This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series 2, Reston Recordings, is a collection of 56 audiotape reels containing Music Center performances by both faculty and students from 1969-1972. This series is arranged alphabetically by the name of the recorded performance.
Series 3 consists of digitized duplicates of the recordings in Series 2. There are audio discs of the recordings as well as digital files on an external drive. The arrangement follows that of Series.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by Loren Bruce of the Reston Historical Trust.
Access Restrictions
Only the digitized recordings are available for listening.
Historical Information
The Northern Virginia Music Center at Reston was established in 1967, and held its first summer camp for young musicians that same year. Initially, its founders aspired to develop the summer camp into a full-faculty, national summer music training program that would eventually become a year-round high school for the performing arts. Although it never developed into a high school, the Center did manage to draw 150 talented student enrollees who came not only from the Greater Washington area, but also from 30 states and a half dozen foreign countries. From 1969-1972, the Music Center faculty and students held regular concerts in Northern Virginia. In 1972, students and faculty traveled to Lausanne, Switzerland, to participate in a series of concerts. By the mid-1970s, the Music Center encountered budget problems, and many board members, including the president, Paul S. Frick, resigned and the Center gradually dissolved. The collection contains some materials from 1978 since some students and faculty from the Center later became associated with the Northern Virginia Youth Symphony Association.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by subject.
Series 1: Music Center Papers, 1967-1979 (Boxes 1-2)
Series 2: Reston Recordings, 1969-1972 (Boxes 2-6)
Series 3: Digital Duplicates, 1969-1972 (Boxes 7-9)
Index Terms
Reston (Va.)
Subjects:
Music.
Document Types:
Live sound recordings.; Photographic prints.
Contents List
- Series 1: Music Center Papers, 1967-1978; (1.5 boxes)
  Series 1, Music Center Papers, 1967-1979, consists of correspondence, programs, articles, and photographs documenting the Center and its performances.
  - Budgets and Fundraising, 1968-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Concerts and Publicity, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Directories and Lists, 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Head Shots of Musicians, 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Heyde, Norma, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letterhead, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Member Correspondence, 1967-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mission Statement, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Music Center Board, 1968-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Music Center By-laws and Amendments, 1968-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Music Center Pamphlets, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Music Center Photographs, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ogg, Janette, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Persichetti, Vincent, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Pfohl, Henry, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Pfohl, James Christian, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Poliakine, David, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Pollack, Daniel, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Reston Music Center Personnel Directory, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The School Musician, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series 2: Reston Recordings, 1969-1972; (4.5 boxes)
  Series 2, Reston Recordings, is a collection of 56 audiotape reels containing Music Center performances by both faculty and students.
  - Aaron Rosand, July 14, 1972 (Box 2, Reel 8)
  - Concert, June 30, 1972 (Box 2, Reel 9)
  - Concert in Tent, 1968 (Box 2, Reel 10)
  - Concert in Tent, 1968 (Box 3, Reel 1)
  - Concert on Plaza, Undated (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - Concerto, August 8, 1970 (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - Eighth Concert, July 16, 1969 (Box 3, Reel 4)
  - Eleventh Concert, July 16, 1971 (Box 3, Reel 5)
  - Elijah-Reston Chorale, May 1, 1970 (Box 3, Reel 6)
  - Faculty Concert, July 21, 1971 (Box 3, Reel 7)
  - Faculty Concert, July 19, 1972 (Box 3, Reel 8)
  - Faculty Concert, July 7, 1972 (Box 3, Reel 9)
  - Faculty Concert, July 12, 1972 (Box 3, Reel 10)
  - Faculty Concert, June 28, 1972 (Box 3, Reel 11)
  - Faculty Concert, July, 28 1972 (Box 3, Reel 12)
  - Faculty Concert, July 5, 1972 (Box 4, Reel 1)
  - Faculty Concert, July 26, 1972 (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - Faculty Concert, July 1, 1970 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - Faculty Concert, July 14, 1970 (Box 4, Reel 4)
  - Faculty Concert, July 29, 1970 (Box 4, Reel 5)
  - Faculty Concert, July 8, 1970 (Box 4, Reel 6)
  - Faculty Concert, July 7, 1971 (Box 4, Reel 7)
  - Final Concert, August 4, 1972 (Box 4, Reel 8)
  - First Baptist Church, 1969 (Box 4, Reel 9)
  - First Concert, June 29, 1971 (Box 4, Reel 10)
  - Fourth Concert, July 5, 1970 (Box 4, Reel 11)
  - Handel-Messiah, December, 1969 (Box 4, Reel 12)
  - John Terry, Tenor, July 21, 1972 (Box 4, Reel 13)
  - Last Concert Before Trip to Switzerland, July 22, 1971 (Box 5, Reel 1)
  - Music Center at Reston Presents Handel's Messiah, December 10, 1971 (Box 5, Reel 2)
  - National Anthem, August 3, 1969 (Box 5, Reel 3)
  - National Cathedral, August 12, 1972 (Box 5, Reel 4)
  - National Cathedral, July 6, 1972 (Box 5, Reel 5)
  - New Town Concert, October 17, 1971 (Box 5, Reel 6)
  - New Town Concert, October 23, 1970 (Box 5, Reel 7)
  - Northern Virginia Music Center Orchestra, August 8, 1970 (Box 5, Reel 8)
  - Northern Virginia Music Center Orchestra, July 24, 1970 (Box 5, Reel 9)
  - Pfohl, Arizzi, Heyde, July 26, 1970 (Box 5, Reel 10)
  - Reston Chamber Orchestra, April 17, 1970 (Box 5, Reel 11)
  - Reston Chamber Orchestra, March 19, 1971 (Box 5, Reel 12)
  - Reston Chorale, November 14, 1970 (Box 5, Reel 13)
  - Reston Trio, January 1, 1970 (Box 5, Reel 14)
  - Second Concert, July 2, 1971 (Box 6, Reel 1)
  - Sixth Concert, July 9, 1971 (Box 6, Reel 2)
  - Student Concert, July 8, 1972 (Box 6, Reel 3)
  - Student Concert, August 2, 1972 (Box 6, Reel 4)
  - Student Concert, July 29, 1972 (Box 6, Reel 5)
  - Student Concert, July 18, 1969 (Box 6, Reel 6)
  - Student Concert, August 5, 1970 (Box 6, Reel 7)
  - Student Recital, July 10, 1971 (Box 6, Reel 8)
  - Sunday, July 12, 1970 (Box 6, Reel 9)
  - The Creation, April 16, 1972 (Box 6, Reel 10)
  - Twelfth Concert, July 19, 1970 (Box 6, Reel 11)
  - Twentieth Concert, August 2, 1970 (Box 6, Reel 12)
  - Twenty-sixth Concert, August 9, 1970 (Box 6, Reel 13)
  - Untitled Recording, Undated (Box 6, Reel 14)
- Series 3: Digital Duplicates, 1969-1972; (3 boxes)
  This series consists of digital duplicates created in 2014 from the open reel tapes of the original concerts. The open reel audio was saved as MP3 and WAV and stored on nine compact discs and an external hard drive. Recordings are arranged in the same order as the recordings in Series 2.
  - Audio discs, 1969-1972 (Box 7)
  - Audio discs, 1969-1972 (Box 8)
  - Audio discs and external drive, 1969-1972 (Box 9)